<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<w:document xmlns:wpc="http://schemas.microsoft.com/office/word/2010/wordprocessingCanvas" xmlns:cx="http://schemas.microsoft.com/office/drawing/2014/chartex" xmlns:cx1="http://schemas.microsoft.com/office/drawing/2015/9/8/chartex" xmlns:cx2="http://schemas.microsoft.com/office/drawing/2015/10/21/chartex" xmlns:cx3="http://schemas.microsoft.com/office/drawing/2016/5/9/chartex" xmlns:cx4="http://schemas.microsoft.com/office/drawing/2016/5/10/chartex" xmlns:cx5="http://schemas.microsoft.com/office/drawing/2016/5/11/chartex" xmlns:cx6="http://schemas.microsoft.com/office/drawing/2016/5/12/chartex" xmlns:cx7="http://schemas.microsoft.com/office/drawing/2016/5/13/chartex" xmlns:cx8="http://schemas.microsoft.com/office/drawing/2016/5/14/chartex" xmlns:mc="http://schemas.openxmlformats.org/markup-compatibility/2006" xmlns:aink="http://schemas.microsoft.com/office/drawing/2016/ink" xmlns:am3d="http://schemas.microsoft.com/office/drawing/2017/model3d" xmlns:o="urn:schemas-microsoft-com:office:office" xmlns:oel="http://schemas.microsoft.com/office/2019/extlst" xmlns:r="http://schemas.openxmlformats.org/officeDocument/2006/relationships" xmlns:m="http://schemas.openxmlformats.org/officeDocument/2006/math" xmlns:v="urn:schemas-microsoft-com:vml" xmlns:wp14="http://schemas.microsoft.com/office/word/2010/wordprocessingDrawing" xmlns:wp="http://schemas.openxmlformats.org/drawingml/2006/wordprocessingDrawing" xmlns:w10="urn:schemas-microsoft-com:office:word" xmlns:w="http://schemas.openxmlformats.org/wordprocessingml/2006/main" xmlns:w14="http://schemas.microsoft.com/office/word/2010/wordml" xmlns:w15="http://schemas.microsoft.com/office/word/2012/wordml" xmlns:w16cex="http://schemas.microsoft.com/office/word/2018/wordml/cex" xmlns:w16cid="http://schemas.microsoft.com/office/word/2016/wordml/cid" xmlns:w16="http://schemas.microsoft.com/office/word/2018/wordml" xmlns:w16du="http://schemas.microsoft.com/office/word/2023/wordml/word16du" xmlns:w16sdtdh="http://schemas.microsoft.com/office/word/2020/wordml/sdtdatahash" xmlns:w16sdtfl="http://schemas.microsoft.com/office/word/2024/wordml/sdtformatlock" xmlns:w16se="http://schemas.microsoft.com/office/word/2015/wordml/symex" xmlns:wpg="http://schemas.microsoft.com/office/word/2010/wordprocessingGroup" xmlns:wpi="http://schemas.microsoft.com/office/word/2010/wordprocessingInk" xmlns:wne="http://schemas.microsoft.com/office/word/2006/wordml" xmlns:wps="http://schemas.microsoft.com/office/word/2010/wordprocessingShape" mc:Ignorable="w14 w15 w16se w16cid w16 w16cex w16sdtdh w16sdtfl w16du wp14"><w:body><w:p w14:paraId="0F04293B" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000"><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="1"/></w:pPr><w:bookmarkStart w:id="0" w:name="master-project-draft-v3"/><w:r><w:t>MASTER PROJECT – DRAFT V3</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="2DAE668B" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000"><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="1"/></w:pPr><w:bookmarkStart w:id="1" w:name="controllable-generative-students"/><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="0"/><w:r><w:t>Controllable Generative Students:</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="16A0BF7C" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000"><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="2"/></w:pPr><w:bookmarkStart w:id="2" w:name="X39b9bf8d4de75b5c5d750a8e433ff98a3c840e9"/><w:r><w:t>Skill-Level Retention and Structured Forgetting in Large Language Models</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="2FDEBB7C" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000"><w:r><w:pict w14:anchorId="39F8ADD4"><v:rect id="_x0000_i1025" style="width:0;height:1.5pt" o:hralign="center" o:hrstd="t" o:hr="t"/></w:pict></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="0ECB49CF" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000"><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="2"/></w:pPr><w:bookmarkStart w:id="3" w:name="abstract"/><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="2"/><w:r><w:t>Abstract</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="27DB41CC" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000"><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="FirstParagraph"/></w:pPr><w:r><w:t>Large Language Models (LLMs) achieve near-expert performance on structured mathematical benchmarks, frequently exceeding 95% accuracy across grade-level assessments. While such performance is advantageous for reasoning applications, it presents a challenge in the context of teacher preparation simulators. The transition from academic training to real classroom practice is a critical phase in novice teachers’ professional development, requiring exposure to heterogeneous classrooms, partial student mastery, and authentic error patterns that are rarely reflected in high-performing models. A classroom simulation environment designed for early-career teachers therefore requires controllable, imperfect learners that reflect differentiated skill profiles rather than uniformly high accuracy.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="21780069" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000"><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="a0"/></w:pPr><w:r><w:t>This master’s project introduces a formal framework for controllable generative students — LLM-based agents that simulate predefined patterns of skill retention and forgetting. We represent student knowledge using explicit binary skill vectors and design prompt-based control mechanisms to enforce selective mastery constraints. Unlike traditional evaluation paradigms that emphasize correctness, we propose controllability-oriented metrics that quantify whether a model forgets when instructed and retains when required, independently of its baseline performance. More specifically, we measure the extent to which the model can faithfully reflect the behavior of a student with learning gaps — not merely by lowering accuracy, but by exhibiting structured, skill-aligned deficiencies consistent with the predefined mastery vector.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="13B472B2" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000"><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="a0"/></w:pPr><w:r><w:t>Using structured MathCAMPS multi-grade datasets with explicit skill tagging, we conduct controlled experiments across multiple LLMs under different prompting strategies (rule-based, few-shot, and hybrid). We introduce a relative loss metric and a skill-level controllability score that capture selective compliance fidelity.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="0CA0D322" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000"><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="a0"/></w:pPr><w:r><w:t>Results demonstrate that controllability is achievable and can be reliably induced, though its magnitude varies across prompting strategies and model architectures. The proposed framework establishes a reproducible methodology for evaluating skill-aware behavioral control in LLM-based educational simulations.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="10D0893C" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000"><w:r><w:lastRenderedPageBreak/><w:pict w14:anchorId="14316068"><v:rect id="_x0000_i1026" style="width:0;height:1.5pt" o:hralign="center" o:hrstd="t" o:hr="t"/></w:pict></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="2B2D7A05" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000"><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="2"/></w:pPr><w:bookmarkStart w:id="4" w:name="introduction"/><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="3"/><w:r><w:t>1. Introduction</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="0AAEE6A4" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000"><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="FirstParagraph"/></w:pPr><w:r><w:t>Large Language Models have rapidly reached state-of-the-art performance across reasoning-intensive tasks, including structured mathematical assessments. Recent evaluations demonstrate that frontier models frequently achieve accuracy levels comparable to high-performing students.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="72D2C65D" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000"><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="a0"/></w:pPr><w:r><w:t>However, high accuracy alone is insufficient for educational simulation.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="1B10E51C" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000"><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="a0"/></w:pPr><w:r><w:t>Teacher-training systems require simulated learners who exhibit structured misconceptions, demonstrate partial mastery, make systematic domain-specific errors, and fail selectively and predictably. In addition, a computational simulation system enables precise repetition and replay of instructional sequences — a capability that is difficult to achieve in current human-based simulation settings — thereby supporting systematic reflection and controlled pedagogical experimentation.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="72321871" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000"><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="a0"/></w:pPr><w:r><w:t>In contrast, modern LLMs exhibit strong global competence. When instructed to “forget” a concept, they often continue to solve related problems correctly due to deeply internalized representations acquired during large-scale pretraining.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="06E0ACE0" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000"><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="a0"/></w:pPr><w:r><w:t>This mismatch exposes a fundamental gap:</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="7454D0BC" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000"><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="aa"/></w:pPr><w:r><w:t>Accuracy is not equivalent to controllability.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="74D8A172" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000"><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="FirstParagraph"/></w:pPr><w:r><w:t>This master’s project investigates the following central research question:</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="35B69B02" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000"><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="a0"/></w:pPr><w:r><w:t>Can we configure a prompted LLM to selectively forget certain skills and knowledge while reliably retaining others?</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="39657AA9" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000"><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="a0"/></w:pPr><w:r><w:t>To address this, we introduce the concept of a controllable generative student — an LLM agent governed by an explicit skill mastery profile that constrains its generative behavior.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="051F848F" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000"><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="3"/></w:pPr><w:bookmarkStart w:id="5" w:name="contributions"/><w:r><w:t>Contributions</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="252D094A" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000"><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="FirstParagraph"/></w:pPr><w:r><w:t>This work makes four primary contributions. First, it introduces a formal skill representation based on a binary skill-vector framework for explicit mastery specification. Second, it develops prompt-based control mechanisms that enforce selective retention and forgetting. Third, it proposes controllability-oriented metrics, including a relative loss formulation that separates compliance from baseline performance. Fourth, it defines a reproducible evaluation methodology across prompting strategies and models.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="4BCA1D38" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000"><w:r><w:pict w14:anchorId="454C322C"><v:rect id="_x0000_i1027" style="width:0;height:1.5pt" o:hralign="center" o:hrstd="t" o:hr="t"/></w:pict></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="23CFD62C" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000"><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="2"/></w:pPr><w:bookmarkStart w:id="6" w:name="Xf12849bf9d76d5a35af8a3530c3c1fecf8c980f"/><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="4"/><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="5"/><w:r><w:lastRenderedPageBreak/><w:t>2. Theoretical Background and Literature Review</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="77580DE1" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000"><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="3"/></w:pPr><w:bookmarkStart w:id="7" w:name="Xbf429059e4a899b63c2a9655649d9115a03d340"/><w:r><w:t>2.1 Induction of Novice Teachers and Opportunities for LLM Integration</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="08195DEA" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000"><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="FirstParagraph"/></w:pPr><w:r><w:t>The transition from academic preparation to real classroom teaching is widely recognized as a critical stage in novice teachers’ professional development. Research on induction programs highlights the importance of structured mentoring, guided reflection, peer collaboration, and emotional support in strengthening professional identity and reducing burnout (Ingersoll &amp; Strong, 2011; Goldberg &amp; Orland-Barak, 2016). Deliberate practice theory further emphasizes the need for repeated, structured engagement with targeted challenges under controlled conditions in order to refine expertise (Ericsson, Krampe, &amp; Tesch-Römer, 1993). However, authentic classroom environments are inherently variable, limiting the ability to recreate identical instructional situations for repeated practice (Heffernan &amp; Heffernan, 2014). This creates an opportunity for computational simulation environments that enable controlled repetition of pedagogical scenarios while maintaining curricular alignment.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="50348025" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000"><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="3"/></w:pPr><w:bookmarkStart w:id="8" w:name="Xb6196e3a71eae1d166bfe0cd14d7e9881b10953"/><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="7"/><w:r><w:t>2.2 LLM-Driven Simulations in Teacher Training</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="0924F6BE" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000"><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="FirstParagraph"/></w:pPr><w:r><w:t>Recent advances in large language models have enabled the development of simulation environments in which virtual students respond according to predefined characteristics. Zhang et al. (2024) demonstrated that LLM-empowered classroom agents can simulate differentiated student behavior, including intentional errors and varying engagement levels. Similarly, Sun et al. (2024) highlighted the potential of LLM-driven educational simulations for scalable and personalized learning environments. These studies show qualitative alignment between predefined profiles and generated behavior, yet they do not systematically quantify the degree of behavioral adherence to a formally specified mastery structure.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="6A1A8EB1" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000"><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="3"/></w:pPr><w:bookmarkStart w:id="9" w:name="embedding-profiles-and-personas-in-llms"/><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="8"/><w:r><w:t>2.3 Embedding Profiles and Personas in LLMs</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="17E11AEF" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000"><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="FirstParagraph"/></w:pPr><w:r><w:t>Research on persona conditioning demonstrates that LLMs can adopt predefined behavioral traits through prompt design. PersonaLLM (Feng et al., 2023) showed that models can maintain stylistic and personality consistency across interactions, although perfect coherence remains challenging. In the educational domain, Lu and Wang (2024) introduced the concept of Generative Students, in which LLMs simulate learners with explicit skill profiles represented as binary mastery vectors. Their framework demonstrated that LLMs can condition responses on predefined knowledge states. Building on this foundation, the present project focuses specifically on controlled skill suppression and formal measurement of selective forgetting.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="31D2F541" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000"><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="3"/></w:pPr><w:bookmarkStart w:id="10" w:name="Xe4aec545c701c9d6956486a5355d3049b241981"/><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="9"/><w:r><w:lastRenderedPageBreak/><w:t>2.4 Knowledge Tracing and Skill Gap Identification</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="05177B75" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000"><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="FirstParagraph"/></w:pPr><w:r><w:t>Knowledge Tracing models provide a probabilistic framework for estimating learner mastery over time. Bayesian Knowledge Tracing and its extensions model transitions between known and unknown states, while deep learning approaches such as Deep Knowledge Tracing (Piech et al., 2015), Dynamic Key-Value Memory Networks (Zhang et al., 2017), and Self-Attentive Knowledge Tracing (Pandey &amp; Karypis, 2019) update skill states based on sequential interactions. Gervet et al. (2020) evaluated when deep models outperform classical approaches in diagnosing learner knowledge. More recently, SkillGapGPT (2025) leveraged LLMs to identify skill gaps directly from student responses, reporting strong alignment with expert annotations. These approaches focus on detecting or predicting knowledge states, whereas the present work focuses on deliberately inducing predefined knowledge gaps in a controlled simulation context.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="70E7FDDC" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000"><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="3"/></w:pPr><w:bookmarkStart w:id="11" w:name="Xfffff2123348a18e8685901163cc9db5ef4e44f"/><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="10"/><w:r><w:t>2.5 Evaluation of Generative Student Behavior</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="0F02D045" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000" w:rsidP="002629EA"><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="FirstParagraph"/><w:jc w:val="both"/></w:pPr><w:r><w:t>Evaluation in educational modeling commonly relies on quantitative metrics such as accuracy, RMSE, AUC, precision, recall, and F1 score (Gervet et al., 2020; SkillGapGPT, 2025). These metrics assess predictive performance or alignment between inferred and true skill states. However, traditional evaluation paradigms emphasize correctness rather than controllability. The current project extends these quantitative evaluation principles by introducing a controllability-oriented formulation that measures the degree to which generated responses align with a predefined mastery vector, thereby distinguishing between raw performance and structured behavioral compliance.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="79FC978B" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000"><w:r><w:pict w14:anchorId="172DAB43"><v:rect id="_x0000_i1028" style="width:0;height:1.5pt" o:hralign="center" o:hrstd="t" o:hr="t"/></w:pict></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="6A4E9D57" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000"><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="2"/></w:pPr><w:bookmarkStart w:id="12" w:name="problem-formulation"/><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="6"/><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="11"/><w:r><w:t>3. Problem Formulation</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="64F6F788" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000"><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="FirstParagraph"/></w:pPr><w:r><w:t>Let S = {s1, s2, …, sn} be the set of skill domains.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="71830FF1" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000"><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="a0"/></w:pPr><w:r><w:t>Let k ∈ {0,1}^n be the mastery vector where k_i = 1 denotes a retained skill and k_i = 0 denotes a forgotten skill.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="4C079433" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000"><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="a0"/></w:pPr><w:r><w:t>This formulation allows us to simulate students with controlled learning gaps through selective subtraction of skills. A “perfect” student is represented by a full mastery vector:</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="59CD47E9" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000"><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="a0"/></w:pPr><w:r><w:t>k = [1,1,1,…,1]</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="334C9840" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000"><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="a0"/></w:pPr><w:r><w:t>In contrast, an “imperfect” student with learning gaps is represented by a partially deactivated vector, for example:</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="1C79AA97" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000"><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="a0"/></w:pPr><w:r><w:t>k = [1,0,1,…]</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="02922672" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000"><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="a0"/></w:pPr><w:r><w:lastRenderedPageBreak/><w:t>where specific skills are intentionally suppressed. The objective of the project is therefore not to reduce global performance, but to induce structured, domain-specific deficiencies that reflect realistic student profiles.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="3BD990BF" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000"><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="a0"/></w:pPr><w:r><w:t>For each skill s_i, q0 denotes the baseline accuracy without forgetting constraints and q1 denotes the accuracy under the controlled prompt.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="2492C51C" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000"><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="3"/></w:pPr><w:bookmarkStart w:id="13" w:name="relative-loss"/><w:r><w:t>Relative Loss</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="2DA085DC" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000"><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="FirstParagraph"/></w:pPr><w:r><w:t>r_i = (q0 - q1) / q0</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="023C15BA" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000"><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="a0"/></w:pPr><w:r><w:t>Interpretation:</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="561A3B03" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000"><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact"/><w:numPr><w:ilvl w:val="0"/><w:numId w:val="2"/></w:numPr></w:pPr><w:r><w:t>If k_i = 0: r_i → 1 desirable</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="4756D602" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000"><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact"/><w:numPr><w:ilvl w:val="0"/><w:numId w:val="2"/></w:numPr></w:pPr><w:r><w:t>If k_i = 1: r_i → 0 desirable</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="695CD521" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000"><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="3"/></w:pPr><w:bookmarkStart w:id="14" w:name="controllability-score"/><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="13"/><w:r><w:t>Controllability Score</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="29693AFE" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000"><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="FirstParagraph"/></w:pPr><w:r><w:t>score_i = (1 - k_i) · r_i - k_i · |r_i|</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="4508DA3F" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000"><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="a0"/></w:pPr><w:r><w:t>Overall:</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="7FA970A9" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000"><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="a0"/></w:pPr><w:r><w:t>Score = (1 / n) ∑ score_i</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="2253F211" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000"><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="a0"/></w:pPr><w:r><w:t>This formulation ensures reward for correct forgetting, penalty for unintended degradation, and independence from absolute baseline performance.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="097A3498" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000"><w:r><w:pict w14:anchorId="4E0FE4AF"><v:rect id="_x0000_i1029" style="width:0;height:1.5pt" o:hralign="center" o:hrstd="t" o:hr="t"/></w:pict></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="30406A76" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000"><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="2"/></w:pPr><w:bookmarkStart w:id="15" w:name="data-description"/><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="12"/><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="14"/><w:r><w:t>4. Data Description</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="3240F008" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000"><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="FirstParagraph"/></w:pPr><w:r><w:t>The empirical framework is built upon the MathCAMPS dataset, which contains curriculum-aligned mathematics problems tagged according to U.S. Common Core standards. Each educational standard is mapped to a Domain, and in the context of this project, each Domain is treated as a distinct Skill. This mapping enables a direct transformation from educational standards to a structured skill taxonomy suitable for controllable simulation.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="00454178" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000"><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="a0"/></w:pPr><w:r><w:t>To ensure fine-grained control and fair evaluation, the dataset was reorganized into eight separate grade-level datasets corresponding to grades 1 through 8. Each grade-specific dataset contains 100 multiple-choice questions, balanced across the relevant skill domains for that grade. Every question was artificially converted into a four-option multiple-choice format (A–D), where distractors were either numerically close to the correct answer or conceptually plausible alternatives. The balanced distribution across skills ensures that per-skill evaluation is statistically stable and that no single skill disproportionately influences aggregate metrics.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="7BED54E8" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000"><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="a0"/></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">During preprocessing and evaluation, certain items were identified as systematically ambiguous or poorly constructed due to repeated cross-model </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:lastRenderedPageBreak/><w:t>errors potentially stemming from the limited mathematical reasoning capabilities of current LLMs of LLMs rather than the intended skill gap. These items were replaced with alternatives from the same educational standard while preserving skill balance. This quality-control stage ensured that subsequent forgetting behavior could be attributed to controlled skill manipulation rather than dataset artifacts.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="5ADF50F3" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000"><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="a0"/></w:pPr><w:r><w:t>Per-skill mastery is computed using the normalized_skill_rank_vector, defined as the number of correct responses associated with a skill divided by the number of items tagged with that skill. This representation enables direct comparison between the intended binary mastery vector and the observed performance profile.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="44316E7E" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000"><w:r><w:pict w14:anchorId="52C4E205"><v:rect id="_x0000_i1030" style="width:0;height:1.5pt" o:hralign="center" o:hrstd="t" o:hr="t"/></w:pict></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="3768A70C" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000"><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="2"/></w:pPr><w:bookmarkStart w:id="16" w:name="methodology"/><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="15"/><w:r><w:t>5. Methodology</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="44DD57F1" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000"><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="3"/></w:pPr><w:bookmarkStart w:id="17" w:name="baseline-the-perfect-student-upper-bound"/><w:r><w:t>5.0 Baseline: The Perfect Student Upper Bound</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="7A83978E" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000"><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="FirstParagraph"/></w:pPr><w:r><w:t>Before introducing controlled forgetting, it is necessary to establish whether modern language models can reliably simulate a perfect student. A Perfect Student is defined as a generative agent whose mastery vector is k = [1,1,1,…,1], implying full mastery across all skills. This configuration serves as an upper performance bound and validates that any later degradation in accuracy originates from deliberate skill suppression rather than inherent model incapacity.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="255A2F14" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000"><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="a0"/></w:pPr><w:r><w:t>Multiple state-of-the-art language models were evaluated under this full-mastery configuration. Across grade-level datasets, several frontier models achieved performance exceeding 95% accuracy, demonstrating that near-perfect curriculum-aligned behavior is attainable. This baseline provides both a performance ceiling and methodological confidence that subsequent errors in imperfect configurations reflect controlled knowledge gaps rather than systemic failure.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="0FCCDBEC" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000"><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="3"/></w:pPr><w:bookmarkStart w:id="18" w:name="generative-student-definition"/><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="17"/><w:r><w:t>5.1 Generative Student Definition</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="411DB56A" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000"><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="FirstParagraph"/></w:pPr><w:r><w:t>Each simulated student is defined by a binary skill vector k, a structured textual description of mastered and missing skills, and fixed decoding parameters. The student profile is dynamically injected into the prompt template using programmatic formatting, enabling scalable generation of diverse student populations with reproducible knowledge configurations.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="2BC584B1" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000"><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="a0"/></w:pPr><w:r><w:t>A perfect student corresponds to a fully activated vector, whereas imperfect students are generated by selectively deactivating one or more skills. This controlled subtraction mechanism enables systematic study of how models respond when specific competencies are intentionally removed.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="53804454" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000"><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="3"/></w:pPr><w:bookmarkStart w:id="19" w:name="prompting-strategies"/><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="18"/><w:r><w:lastRenderedPageBreak/><w:t>5.2 Prompting Strategies</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="7ACA3609" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000"><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="FirstParagraph"/></w:pPr><w:r><w:t>Three prompting strategies were implemented within a unified prompt structure. The rule-based strategy provides explicit behavioral constraints instructing the model to answer correctly when a skill is mastered and to produce consistent mistakes when the skill is missing. The few-shot strategy supplies skill-aligned demonstration examples that illustrate both correct and incorrect behavior patterns. To prevent data leakage, few-shot examples are retrieved from an external file fully separated from the evaluation datasets. The combined strategy integrates explicit behavioral rules with concrete demonstrations to reinforce consistency and realism.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="3A87EA36" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000"><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="a0"/></w:pPr><w:r><w:t>Each generated prompt follows a consistent architecture that includes the student’s mastered and missing skills, behavioral instructions and/or examples, and the current multiple-choice question. The model is instructed to return exactly one answer option without explanation, ensuring standardized output suitable for quantitative analysis.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="0B30E5AC" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000"><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="3"/></w:pPr><w:bookmarkStart w:id="20" w:name="experimental-protocol"/><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="19"/><w:r><w:t>5.3 Experimental Protocol</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="6DE7B8F8" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000"><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="FirstParagraph"/></w:pPr><w:r><w:t>For each model, we performed multiple independent runs per configuration, evaluated multiple skill profiles, executed the full test per profile, logged per-question predictions, and aggregated results by skill domain.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="6DAFF8DA" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000"><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="3"/></w:pPr><w:bookmarkStart w:id="21" w:name="evaluation-metrics"/><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="20"/><w:r><w:t>5.4 Evaluation Metrics</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="12EABFA7" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000"><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="FirstParagraph"/></w:pPr><w:r><w:t>Evaluation operates at the student–model pair level, aggregated across all test items. Per-skill accuracy is computed and compared to the original binary mastery vector. Relative loss and the controllability score quantify selective forgetting and retention behavior, while RMSE measures overall deviation between intended and observed skill profiles.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="52C73844" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000"><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="a0"/></w:pPr><w:r><w:t>In addition to these scalar metrics, the framework incorporates a Cross-Skill Influence Matrix. For each simulated configuration in which a specific skill is deactivated, performance changes are measured not only on the targeted skill (diagonal elements) but also on all other skills (off-diagonal elements). The diagonal entries quantify direct forgetting effectiveness, whereas off-diagonal entries capture unintended cross-skill interference. A robust prompting mechanism should localize performance degradation to the intentionally removed skill while minimizing collateral impact on retained competencies. This matrix therefore provides a structural evaluation of whether the model simulates independent competencies or exhibits entangled knowledge representations.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="3FC6774C" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000"><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="a0"/></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Together, these metrics measure how accurately the model reflects the intended student profile, how effectively prompting enforces selective forgetting, and </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:lastRenderedPageBreak/><w:t>whether induced knowledge gaps remain isolated at the skill level rather than propagating across unrelated domains.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="3BDB7C58" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000"><w:r><w:pict w14:anchorId="661FA87D"><v:rect id="_x0000_i1031" style="width:0;height:1.5pt" o:hralign="center" o:hrstd="t" o:hr="t"/></w:pict></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="6E3E1EB9" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000"><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="2"/></w:pPr><w:bookmarkStart w:id="22" w:name="experiments"/><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="16"/><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="21"/><w:r><w:t>6. Experiments</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="602D887B" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000"><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="FirstParagraph"/></w:pPr><w:r><w:t>The experimental pipeline consists of four stages. First, the Perfect Student configuration establishes the upper bound performance across grade-level datasets. Second, controlled skill forgetting experiments systematically deactivate individual skills to evaluate selective suppression. Third, prompt ablation experiments compare rule-based, few-shot, and combined strategies under identical student profiles. Fourth, variance analysis examines stability across repeated executions.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="4DD9B877" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000"><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="a0"/></w:pPr><w:r><w:t>Each experiment is conducted separately for every grade-level dataset to ensure that skill distributions remain internally consistent. Results are aggregated per skill, per student profile, and per model.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="348688A5" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000"><w:r><w:pict w14:anchorId="678FB8F8"><v:rect id="_x0000_i1032" style="width:0;height:1.5pt" o:hralign="center" o:hrstd="t" o:hr="t"/></w:pict></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="2834EC7F" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000"><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="2"/></w:pPr><w:bookmarkStart w:id="23" w:name="results"/><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="22"/><w:r><w:t>7. Results</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="116193B7" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000" w:rsidP="002629EA"><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="FirstParagraph"/><w:jc w:val="both"/></w:pPr><w:r><w:t>Baseline evaluation confirms that several frontier language models can simulate near-perfect students with high consistency, frequently exceeding 95% accuracy across grade-level datasets. This validates the feasibility of using LLMs as reliable upper-bound knowledge holders before introducing controlled imperfections.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="676C8335" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000" w:rsidP="002629EA"><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="a0"/><w:jc w:val="both"/></w:pPr><w:r><w:t>Under controlled forgetting configurations, models demonstrate measurable and structured degradation aligned with the predefined mastery vectors. Relative loss values increase significantly for intentionally removed skills while remaining comparatively stable for retained skills, indicating effective selective suppression.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="48F27D24" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000" w:rsidP="002629EA"><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="a0"/><w:jc w:val="both"/></w:pPr><w:r><w:t>Prompting strategy comparison reveals that the combined approach generally produces the strongest alignment with intended skill profiles, suggesting that explicit rules reinforced by demonstrations enhance controllability. Cross-skill influence analysis shows that well-configured prompts localize performance drops primarily to targeted skills, with limited off-diagonal interference, supporting the structural independence of competencies under appropriate control settings.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="19B7B5B5" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000" w:rsidP="002629EA"><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="a0"/><w:jc w:val="both"/></w:pPr><w:r><w:t>Variance analysis indicates stable behavior across repeated executions, reinforcing the reproducibility of the controllable generative student framework.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="37C29C3F" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000"><w:r><w:pict w14:anchorId="0FB80213"><v:rect id="_x0000_i1033" style="width:0;height:1.5pt" o:hralign="center" o:hrstd="t" o:hr="t"/></w:pict></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="3FF0FF45" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000"><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="2"/></w:pPr><w:bookmarkStart w:id="24" w:name="discussion"/><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="23"/><w:r><w:lastRenderedPageBreak/><w:t>8. Discussion</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="1B7DC080" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000"><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="FirstParagraph"/></w:pPr><w:r><w:t>Key analytical dimensions include whether forgetting is controllable or partially suppressed by pretraining, whether prompt complexity increases compliance, whether some skill domains are inherently resistant to forgetting, and how controllability scales across grade levels.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="424EBE73" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000"><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="a0"/></w:pPr><w:r><w:t>The main limitations include reliance on prompt-only control without fine-tuning, the binary mastery assumption, and single-skill tagging per question.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="61ED1459" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000"><w:r><w:pict w14:anchorId="21344FAC"><v:rect id="_x0000_i1034" style="width:0;height:1.5pt" o:hralign="center" o:hrstd="t" o:hr="t"/></w:pict></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="5F327A9D" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000"><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="2"/></w:pPr><w:bookmarkStart w:id="25" w:name="future-work"/><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="24"/><w:r><w:t>9. Future Work</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="2E96C289" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000"><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="FirstParagraph"/></w:pPr><w:r><w:t>Future work includes skill dependency modeling through a hierarchical skill graph, adoption of a continuous mastery scale instead of a binary representation, reinforcement-based controllability tuning, and dynamic forgetting during multi-step reasoning.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="68B1D204" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000"><w:r><w:pict w14:anchorId="6EE138DF"><v:rect id="_x0000_i1035" style="width:0;height:1.5pt" o:hralign="center" o:hrstd="t" o:hr="t"/></w:pict></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="08D2D1E7" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000"><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="2"/></w:pPr><w:bookmarkStart w:id="26" w:name="conclusion"/><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="25"/><w:r><w:t>10. Conclusion</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="1ACB345B" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000"><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="FirstParagraph"/></w:pPr><w:r><w:t>This master’s project establishes that structured skill-level controllability in LLM-based student simulation is measurable and achievable. The proposed metric framework enables rigorous evaluation of selective compliance and provides practical validation for controlled classroom-simulation deployment.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p w14:paraId="00A44BB2" w14:textId="77777777" w:rsidR="008D4EC1" w:rsidRDefault="00000000"><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="a0"/></w:pPr><w:r><w:t>The framework lays foundational methodology for controlled educational LLM deployment in teacher training and simulation systems.</w:t></w:r><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="1"/><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="26"/></w:p><w:sectPr w:rsidR="008D4EC1"><w:footnotePr><w:numRestart w:val="eachSect"/></w:footnotePr><w:pgSz w:w="12240" w:h="15840"/><w:pgMar w:top="1440" w:right="1800" w:bottom="1440" w:left="1800" w:header="720" w:footer="720" w:gutter="0"/><w:cols w:space="720"/></w:sectPr></w:body></w:document>
